A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Press Materials FA1322
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Press Materials
1951-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1322
64.91 Cubic Feet 152 document boxes and 1 oversize document box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains different types of press materials from 1951 to 2002 that document the Ford Foundation's efforts to both publicize itself in the news and acquire documentation of media commentary on its ventures. Within the collection, press releases appear as the most used publicity tool for promoting the Foundation, while press clippings appear as the primary means for collecting media commentary on the Foundation's activities. Most of the press clippings found within the collection were submitted to the Foundation's Office of Communications by press clipping service providers Burrelle's Information Services and Luce Press Clippings in the 1990s and early 2000s.
This collection is composed of multiple records groups. Each one represents one or more accessions of press materials that was transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center and processed at a certain time. These record groups consist of various groupings and subgroupings of press material that are represented by series and subseries. While there are several instances where one record group contains a set of material not found in the other record group, there are also cases where documents from the same set of material are shared between both record groups. Only one instance occurred where material from Record Group 2 was integrated into Record Group 1. An evident gap existed where the News from the Ford Foundation press releases No. 676-735 were meant to go in Record Group 1 Series 1, so the files were moved from Record Group 2 during processing. Other locations where the later accessioned material could be inserted into the already processed holdings were not as evident, so the decision was made to represent the vast majority of Record Group 2 documents as its own entity within a larger press materials collection. The arrangement and description of the series and subseries in Record Group 2 highlight connections to related material in Record Group 1.
Although the Ford Foundation Office of Communications and Office of Reports seem to have had the most amount of responsibility in the creation and use of these records, there is evidence that other departments within the organization had a role in compiling and organizing certain groups of files within the collection. For example, there is a set of subject arranged press release files that were maintained by the Foundation's Education and Culture Program.
Besides press releases and press clippings, the collection contains materials such as correspondence, reports, publications, invoices, radio and television broadcast transcripts, mailing lists, invitation lists, and press logs. There are also a few files that house photographs.
Documents in the collection concern such broad topics as philanthropy, international relations, economic development, the arts and humanities, social justice, civil rights, community development, energy policy, state and local government, population and family planning, and education among others. More specific subjects include immigration, women's rights, women in the workplace, LGBT social activism, diversity in higher education, the reorganization of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), the growth of the Gates Foundation, public suspicion and criticism of government, the 1990s Million Man March, the decentralization of New York City public schools, the appointments of various Ford Foundation presidents, international studies programs, the U.S. House of Representatives investigation into tax-exempt foundations in the 1950s, the role of black fathers, fellowships for various kinds of artists, musicians, and writers, business education, and funding for public broadcasting.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necesary.
The first set of Ford Foundation Press Materials was transferred to the RAC in 2017 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2017:062 and 2017:078. These accessions make up Ford Foundation records, Press Materials, Record Group 1.
Another set of press materials was transferred to the RAC in 2018 and ingested as Accession 2018:088. This accession makes up Ford Foundation records, Press Materials, Record Group 2.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two different record groups, seven series, and seventeen subseries.
Record Group 1 contains the first two accessions (2017:063 and 2017:078) of Ford Foundation press materials transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center and was originally described as a stand-alone collection. Those documents were then represented as a record group when another accession of press materials was received after the first two had been processed. Record Group 2 holds this accession (2018:088).
There were obvious relationships between documents in the processed collection and documents in the new accession, but it was decided during the processing of Accession 2018:088 to represent these connections though the implementation of different records groups within a larger collection rather than to try to integrate the documents in 2018:088 into the established Ford Foundation Press Materials collection. The exception to this strategy occurred with the insertion of News from the Ford Foundation press releases, No. 676-735 from Accession 2018:088 into Record Group 1. Those documents filled a clear gap in the first record group's holdings, and it required minimal interference to restore that contextual relationship.
If future transfers of large amounts of press materials occur, those documents will likely be represented as additional record groups in the collection.
Original order was maintained as much as possible in arranging the collection.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Record Group 1. Accessions 2017:062 and 2017:078, 1951-2002
Record Group 1. Series 1. Press releases, 1951-1975, 1990-1993
Record Group 1. Series 1. Subseries 1. News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 1-295, 1951-1962
Record Group 1. Series 1. Subseries 2. News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 370-771, 1964-1970
Record Group 1. Series 1. Subseries 3. News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 829-1005, 1972-1975
Record Group 1. Series 1. Subseries 4. Press release job files, 1990-1993 Series 2 Press clippings, 1964-2002
Record Group 1. Series 2. Subseries 1. Clippings, announcements, and miscellaneous press media 1964-1998
Record Group 1. Series 2. Subseries 2. Clippings and announcements, 1992-1998
Record Group 1. Series 2. Subseries 3. Clippings and announcements, 1992-2002
Record Group 1. Series 2. Subseries 4. Comment on the Ford Foundation issues, 1974-1988
Record Group 1. Series 3. Press conference and news briefing materials, 1960-1977
Record Group 1. Series 4. Radio and television press media, 1951-1959
Record Group 1. Series 5. Oversize magazine articles, 1968-1969
Record Group 2. Accession 2018:088, 1953-2002
Record Group 2. Series 1. Press releases, 1955-1993
Record Group 2. Series 1. Subseries 1. Education and Culture Program press release subject files, 1956-1981
Record Group 2. Series 1. Subseries 2. News from the Ford Foundation releases by date, 1966-1973
Record Group 2. Series 1. Subseries 3. Press job files, 1955-1993
Record Group 2. Series 1. Subseries 4. Miscellaneous releases, 1979-1991
Record Group 2. Series 2. Press clippings, 1953-2002
Record Group 2. Series 2. Subseries 1. Mayor's Advisory Panel on Decentralization of New York City Schools clippings files, 1966-1969
Record Group 2. Series 2. Subseries 2. Staff members, Trustees, and other individuals' clippings files, 1955-1991
Record Group 2. Series 2. Subseries 3. Office of Reports flap files, 1953-1974
Record Group 2. Series 2. Subseries 4. Clippings, 1983-1998
Record Group 2. Series 2. Subseries 5. Clippings, 2000-2002
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
African Americans -- Civil rights; Agriculture development projects; Architecture; Arts -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Business education; Economic development; Education; Educational television programs; Emigration and immigration; Endowments; Endowments -- Public relations -- United States; Energy policy; Fathers -- Research; Foreign study; Gay rights; International relations; International relations--Study and teaching; Local government; Population; Public opinion; Public television; Scholarships; Sex discrimination against women; Teenage pregnancy; Women's rights
- Record Group 1, Accessions 2017:062 and 2017:078, 1951-2002; 1; 32.713 Cubic Feet 29 LTR size, 1 Half-LTR size, 44 LGL size, and 2 Half-LGL size Hollinger boxes and 1 oversize document box
  Arrangement
  The record group is divided into five series and eight subseries.
  The first four series reflect how the record group material was grouped within the original storage containers of Ford Foundation Press Materials Accessions 2017:062 and 2017:078. Documents appeared to have been organized according to press material type. For instance, some boxes predominately housed press clippings while others predominately housed radio and television press media. The two main press material types discerned during processing were press releases (Series 1) and press clippings (Series 2). They both spanned multiple boxes, encompassing the vast bulk of the collection. The other two press material types – press conference and news briefing materials (Series 3) and radio and television press media (Series 4) – only occupied two respective boxes. However, the materials in both boxes appeared to comprise two distinct groupings of collection material and were therefore represented as separate series.
  The last series consists of four large magazine articles. These articles did not appear to possess any relationship to the groupings of materials found within the other boxes. In consideration of this and of the oversize containers needed to properly house the materials, the articles were included at the end of the collection as a fifth series.
  The first two series were divided into eight subseries (four for Series 1 and four for Series 2) during processing. These subseries represent identified systems of organization within the press release and press clipping groupings, and they help to facilitate improved user access to the large quantity of records that each series possesses.
  Record group arrangement is as follows:
  Series 1. Press releases, 1951-1975, 1990-1993
  Series 1. Subseries 1. News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 1-295, 1951-1962
  Series 1. Subseries 2. News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 370-771, 1964-1970
  Series 1. Subseries 3. News from the Ford Foundation releases No. 829-1005, 1972-1975
  Series 1. Subseries 4. Press release job files, 1990-1993
  Series 2. Press clippings, 1964-2002
  Series 2. Subseries 1. Clippings, announcements, and miscellaneous press media 1964-1998
  Series 2. Subseries 2. Clippings and announcements, 1992-1998
  Series 2. Subseries 3. Clippings and announcements, 1992-2002
  Series 2. Subseries 4. Comment on the Ford Foundation issues, 1974-1988
  Series 3. Press conference and news briefing materials, 1960-1977
  Series 4. Radio and television press media, 1951-1959
  Series 5. Oversize magazine articles, 1968-1969
  Scope and Contents
  This record group contains the first two sets of Ford Foundation press materials transferred to and processed by the Rockefeller Archive Center. They were ingested in 2017 as Accessions 2017:062 and 2017:078 and were described together in the collection finding aid in 2018.
  Within the record group, there are four main types of press material: 1) press releases, 2) press clippings, 3) press conference and news briefing materials, and 4) radio and television press media. Each of these material types are housed within a separate series. A fifth series holds oversize magazine articles from the late 1960s that largely concern the architecture and design of the new Ford Foundation headquarters building in New York City.
  The Ford Foundation's publicity strategy for this time period is most consistently documented by the News from the Ford Foundation press releases in Series 1. These releases belong to an organized system of press releases compiled by the Ford Foundation Office of Reports between 1951 and 1975. Likewise, the Ford Foundation's attempts to collect media commentary on its activities is most consistently documented by the press clippings in Series 2. These clippings were sent to the Ford Foundation Office of Communications by press clipping service providers Burrelle's Information Services and Luce Press Clippings in the 1990s and early 2000s.
  A small amount of material was integrated into the record group from Record Group 2 in order to restore obvious contextual relationships between materials. Similar actions may occur again if future accessions of Ford Foundation press material are transferred to the Archive Center, and the new files fill evident gaps in Record Group 1's holdings.
  - Press releases, 1951-1975, 1990-1993; 1; 9.545 Cubic Feet About 1 half LGL size Hollinger box, 2 full LGL size Hollinger boxes, and 22 LTR size Hollinger boxes
    The series was broken into four subseries during processing in order to represent the two original systems of arrangement found within the series as well as to facilitate improved user access to the large number of files containing the Ford Foundation's press releases. The first three subseries contain press releases that were included within a numbering system devised possibly by the Ford Foundation Office of Reports or by any other entity involved with the creation and/or custodianship of the records. These releases were then divided further into separate subseries based on chronological groupings. The chronological system of arrangement for the first three subseries helps to identify gaps in the records that the record group holds. For example, users can see that the series does not contain press releases No. 296-369 (1962-1964).
    The integration of press releases No. 676-735 (July 1969 – July 1970) from Record Group 2 after the rest of the series had been processed and described helped fill another one of these gaps.
    The fourth subseries consists of press release job files from the early 1990s that were organized by topic and job number.
    The series arrangement is as follows:
    Series primarily consists of Ford Foundation press releases that were published between 1951 and 1975 and between 1990 and 1993. The Foundation disseminated these press releases in order to share news of its latest organizational developments as well as to publicize the most recent and upcoming actions of its various philanthropic programs. Position appointments, grant distributions, fellowship award winners, program expansions, and published reports are all common announcements featured in the series.
    Within the series, the 1951-1975 press release files are distinct from the 1990-1993 files in terms of more than just dates. The 1951-1975 files (with the exception of a few in Series 1 Subseries 1) consist of single press releases that have been organized into a numbered system of news announcements either by the Ford Foundation Office of Reports or by another entity involved with the creation and/or custodianship of the records. These files are all titled News from the Ford Foundation, and they make up the first three subseries. In contrast to the News from the Ford Foundation files, the 1990-1993 press release files contain much more than the finished versions of the disseminated news announcements. They are job files that document how the Ford Foundation created, advertised, and published its press releases. They make up the fourth subseries.
    While all files are titled News from the Ford Foundation in the first three subseries, not all of the actual press releases within those files bear that title. It appears that the records creators adopted that name to reference the entire system of press releases that they organized and numbered. The News from the Ford Foundation system has put the press releases into a mostly chronological order. Obvious revisions to the system indicate that it does not perfectly encompass every press release ever disseminated by the Ford Foundation because the records creators had to go back and add files to the system with numbers like 247a. Furthermore, evident gaps in the series' press release holdings show that the record group does not house the entire News from the Ford Foundation press release system (News from the Ford Foundation press releases No. 676-735 (July 1969 – July 1970) in Series 1 Subseries 2 were originally housed in Record Group 2 and were integrated into this series during the processing of that record group). The records creators also sorted a few unnumbered press releases in other parts of the record group (Series 3 and Series 4).
    Although all of the News from the Ford Foundation press releases were numbered, not all of them had titles that described their content. Titles were therefore supplied to those files that lacked them during processing. Both original and supplied titles were taken from the press release lead in most cases. Researchers should keep this in mind as a file title may not represent all of the information disseminated within a press release.
    Most files in the first three subseries contain multiple copies of the published press releases. Some also contain or are wholly comprised of supplementary documents to press releases such as reports and photographs.
    - News from the Ford Foundation releases, No. 1-295, 1951-1962; 1; 3.19 Cubic Feet About 1 Half LGL sized Hollinger box and 7.75 LTR sized Hollinger boxes
      Subseries contains News from the Ford Foundation press releases No. 1-295. The first three files contain collections of press releases from the early and mid-1950s rather than single releases like all of the other files. However, these files still belong to the numbered system of News from the Ford Foundation press releases as numbers 1, 2, and 3. Press releases within the first three files concern such topics as the Fund for the Republic, the Fund for Adult Education, the U.S. House of Representatives' investigations into tax-exempt foundations, agriculture and food production in India, the National Merit Scholarship Cooperation, Henry Ford II, the appointments of Ford Foundation Presidents H. Rowan Gaither Jr. and Henry T. Heald, and the Foreign Area Training Fellowships Program.
      The subseries does not contain any significant gaps in its holdings.
      - 1. Assorted press releases, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - 2. Assorted press releases, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - 3. Assorted press releases, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
      - 4. Announcements of special 500 million dollar appropriation, 1955 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
        File contains a list of grants awarded as part of the Ford Foundation's special 500-million-dollar appropriation. The actual announcement for the appropriation is housed within Series 1, Subseries 1, File: 3. Assorted press releases, 1955-1956 (Folder 7).
      - 7. Voluntary, non-profit hospital grants, 1956 March (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - 8. First checks of 200 million dollar program for hospitals, 1956 April; File contains one still image captioned "The First Payment". Image shows Dr. Edwin L. Crosby, Director of the American Hospital Association with Dyke Brown, Vice President of the Ford Foundation. (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
      - 9. Second group of hospitals to receive payments, 1956 May 21 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - 10. Third group of payments to hospitals, 1956 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
      - 11. Sampling of Hospital Grant Projects, 1956 October (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - 12. Publication of scholarly books in the humanities and social sciences, 1956 October 7 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - 14. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald address to the National Institute of Social Sciences, 1956 November 30 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - 16. Education programming consolidation, 1956 December 13 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - 17. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald address to the Engineers Joint Council, 1957 January 17 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - 18. American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), 1957 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - 19. Educational opportunity for Hungarian refugee students, 1957 February 6 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - 20. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald address to the Transportation Association of America, 1957 February 13 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - 21. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald statement on OMNIBUS, 1957 February 19 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - 22. Robert Saudek statement on OMNIBUS, 1957 February 19 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - 23. Education activities in the 1956 fiscal year, 1957 February 24 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - 24. Mental health research and behavioral sciences activities in the 1956 fiscal year, 1957 March 3 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - 25. International program activities in the 1956 fiscal year, 1957 March (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - 26. H. Rowan Gaither Jr. address to the Rotary Club of New York, 1957 March 14 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - 27. Final payments to hospitals, 1957 March (Box 4, Folder 35-38)
      - 29. Thomas W. Boynton and Stanley W. Gregory appointments, 1957 March 28 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - 31. National Woodrow Wilson Fellowship Program, 1957 April 4 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - 32. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald address at the Southern University Conference, 1957 April 4 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - 33. Second quarter grants and appropriations, 1957 April (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - 34. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald address to the Economic Club of Detroit, Michigan, 1957 April 8 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - 35. New grants and appropriations, 1957 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - 36. Grant to the Government of India for the training of engineers, 1957 April 22 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - 37. Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald statement to the Executive Club of Chicago, 1957 April 26 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - 38. Foreign Area Training Fellowships, 1957 May 15 (Box 4, Folder 47)